<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.3.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2016-10-27T18:11:50+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000//</id><title type="html">Your awesome title</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Knee Problems 101 – The VMO Solution</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/knee-problems-101-the-vmo-solution-880/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Knee Problems 101 &amp;#8211; The VMO Solution" /><published>2016-01-09T05:04:05+05:30</published><updated>2016-01-09T05:04:05+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/knee-problems-101-the-vmo-solution</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/knee-problems-101-the-vmo-solution-880/">&lt;p&gt;The credit for this post goes entirely to an unknown user on Reddit who posted [this](https://www.reddit.com/r/Fitness/comments/q6bcf/i_just_wanted_to_tell_someone_that_i_finally/). In addition, there’s a lot I learnt from Charles Poliquin’s post on the VMO solution&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-get-the-terminology-right&quot;&gt;Lets get the terminology right.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thigh connects to the knee through what is called the quadriceps. Th quadriceps muscles consists of the following four types:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;·        Rectus femoris&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;·        Vastus lateralis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;·        Vastus intermedius&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;·        Vastus medialis oblique  – a fast twitch fiber (meaning: responds better to higher intensity low rep exercises)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All four muscles are attached to the kneecap (&lt;em&gt;patella&lt;/em&gt;) by the quadriceps tendon. What’s unique about the VMO is that it is the only one of the four muscles to cross the knee. The VMO is activated primarily when the knee is bent past 90 degrees. In most daily activities (and in fact most sports), we rarely bend our knees to beyond 90 degrees. This means that the VMO  develops more structural imbalance  than the other quad muscles….leading to injuries such as jumper’s knee. Jumper’s knee symptoms include aching just below the kneecap, and the injury keeps getting worse until there is constant pain reduced leg strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;detecting-jumpers-knee&quot;&gt;Detecting jumpers knee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to detect a weak VMO is to observe the jump – if you land on your knees and knees buckle inward, meaning that the knee is unstable, that is probably a sign of VMO weakness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Charles Poliquin came up with the idea for this exercise from working with Olympic skiers to offset their enormous upper quad development and prepare their knees better. Rather than waiting for an injury such as jumper’s knee to happen, it’s smart to perform these corrective exercises to prevent it from happening in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;impact-on-performance-sports&quot;&gt;Impact on Performance Sports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;as a sidenote, people who are into performance sports like weightlifting and squats need to fix their VMO . Pat Mendes is the 2011 Senior National Weightlifting Champion and a definite contender for the 2012 Olympics. Pat Mendes has done a full squat with 800 pounds, without special knee wraps or a super suit or even a weightlifting belt. He was treated by Poliquin for weak VMO as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;corrective-exercise&quot;&gt;Corrective Exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Squat down for a 5-second count until you hit bottom position, come up a quarter of the way at a slow and deliberate pace, go back all the way down under control until the hamstrings cover the calves, and then come up until your knees are short of lockout. That consists of one rep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this exercise with or without weights – either ways it should help your VMO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html">The credit for this post goes entirely to an unknown user on Reddit who posted [this](https://www.reddit.com/r/Fitness/comments/q6bcf/i_just_wanted_to_tell_someone_that_i_finally/). In addition, there’s a lot I learnt from Charles Poliquin’s post on the VMO solution</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2016/01/Illu_lower_extremity_muscles.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cutting back sugar (rather than fat/oil) improves children health in 10 days flat</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cutting-back-sugar-rather-than-fatoil-improves-children-health-in-10-days-flat-858/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cutting back sugar (rather than fat/oil) improves children health in 10 days flat" /><published>2015-10-28T04:13:58+05:30</published><updated>2015-10-28T04:13:58+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cutting-back-sugar-rather-than-fatoil-improves-children-health-in-10-days-flat</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cutting-back-sugar-rather-than-fatoil-improves-children-health-in-10-days-flat-858/">&lt;p&gt;A new paper by lead author Robert Lustig (MD, MSL UCSF Benioff Children’s Hospital San Francisco) and Jean-Marc Schwarz (PhD  College of Osteopathic Medicine at Touro University California) hints at the massive improvements to children’s health with just 10 days of cutting sugar from their diets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This paper (still in preprint) has been discussed before at a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.healio.com/endocrinology/obesity/news/online/%7B4cac209c-a2a3-4ec8-83c4-f39774e92535%7D/short-term-fructose-restriction-in-children-reduces-sugar-to-fat-conversion-in-liver&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.healio.com/endocrinology/obesity/news/online/%7B4cac209c-a2a3-4ec8-83c4-f39774e92535%7D/short-term-fructose-restriction-in-children-reduces-sugar-to-fat-conversion-in-liver', 'conference in San Diego']);&quot;&gt;conference in San Diego&lt;/a&gt; as well as being released in Feb 2016 in &lt;em&gt;Obesity&lt;/em&gt; magazine, yet the findings of it are massive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;EDIT: The preprint edition of the paper is &lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/oby.21371/abstract&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/oby.21371/abstract', 'here']);&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/oby.21371/pdf&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/oby.21371/pdf', 'PDF']);&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;). __Lustig, R. H., Mulligan, K., Noworolski, S. M., Tai, V. W., Wen, M. J., Erkin-Cakmak, A., Gugliucci, A. and Schwarz, J.-M. (2015), Isocaloric fructose restriction and metabolic improvement in children with obesity and metabolic syndrome. Obesity. doi: 10.1002/oby.21371. The study was funded directly by the National Institutes of Health.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing consumption of sugar for &lt;em&gt;even 10 days&lt;/em&gt; , even without reducing weight or calories, has the power to reverse a series of chronic diseases (including high cholesterol and blood pressure) in children.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is massive because it does not talk about reducing fat intake or oil or saturated fat (none of which are relevant anyway… as past I have written in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fitosaur.us/credit-suisse-thought-leadership-posts-a-study-in-favor-of-saturated-fats-845/&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.fitosaur.us/credit-suisse-thought-leadership-posts-a-study-in-favor-of-saturated-fats-845/', 'past']);&quot;&gt;past&lt;/a&gt;) . In fact, Robert Lustig mentions “&lt;em&gt;This internally controlled intervention study is a solid indication that sugar contributes to metabolic syndrome, and is the strongest evidence to date that the negative effects of sugar are not because of calories or obesity&lt;/em&gt;“.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caveat: Participants were identified through the Weight Assessment for Teen and Child Health Clinic (WATCH) at UCSF Benioff Children’s Hospital San Francisco, an interdisciplinary obesity clinic dedicated to targeting metabolic dysfunction rather than weight loss. Recruitment was limited to &lt;em&gt;Latino and African-American youth&lt;/em&gt; because of their higher risk for certain conditions associated with metabolic syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;strong&gt;not a survey&lt;/strong&gt;, but a controlled trial – 43 children between the ages of 9 and 18 who were obese were given nine days of food &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;with restricted sugar&lt;/span&gt;, but were carefully given diets to maintain the same fat/protein/carbohydrate  plus calorie levels as their previously reported diets. Very interestingly – they did add other carbohydrates such as bagels, cereal and pasta ! In fact, just taking out the sugar meant the kids felt more full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in just 9 days, every aspect of the kids’ metabolic health improved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The released paper will have more details on this subject – but the information is clear: cut down on sugar (even those in fruit juices) to improve kids health. Leave those egg yolks and butter alone.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html">A new paper by lead author Robert Lustig (MD, MSL UCSF Benioff Children’s Hospital San Francisco) and Jean-Marc Schwarz (PhD  College of Osteopathic Medicine at Touro University California) hints at the massive improvements to children’s health with just 10 days of cutting sugar from their diets.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/543ab6f44216d.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Change your kids diet to avoid deadly peanut allergies</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/change-your-kids-diet-to-avoid-deadly-peanut-allergies-854/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Change your kids diet to avoid deadly peanut allergies" /><published>2015-10-27T05:23:07+05:30</published><updated>2015-10-27T05:23:07+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/change-your-kids-diet-to-avoid-deadly-peanut-allergies</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/change-your-kids-diet-to-avoid-deadly-peanut-allergies-854/">&lt;p&gt;There was a study designed by a team from King’s College London called &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa1414850&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa1414850', 'Learning Early About Peanut Allergy (LEAP)']);&quot;&gt;Learning Early About Peanut Allergy (LEAP)&lt;/a&gt; .  &lt;/strong&gt;It was interesting enought that there is a whole &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leapstudy.co.uk/&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.leapstudy.co.uk/', 'website']);&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; now dedicated to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question it wanted to answer was simple – Should young children eat peanuts or avoid them? Which is a better approach to preventing peanut allergy?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peanut  allergies tend to develop in childhood, usually are lifelong. In the U.S., approximately three million people report allergies to peanuts and tree nuts. Studies show the number of American children living with peanut allergy appears to have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foodallergy.org/facts-and-stats&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'https://www.foodallergy.org/facts-and-stats', 'tripled']);&quot;&gt;tripled&lt;/a&gt; between 1997 and 2008 – it is so bad that presumably 1 in 50 American kids suffers from a peanut allergy. What is even worse is that children with food allergy are 2-4 times more likely to have other related conditions such as asthma and other allergies, compared with children who do not have food allergies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is interesting though is that Israeli kids dont suffer from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMe1500186?af=R&amp;amp;rss=currentIssue&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMe1500186?af=R&amp;amp;rss=currentIssue', 'editorial']);&quot;&gt;editorial&lt;/a&gt; (referring on the actual paper) is an interesting read describing the results as &lt;em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;are so compelling, and the problem of the increasing prevalence of peanut allergy so alarming, new guidelines should be forthcoming very soon. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the study, London based infants (4-11 &lt;strong&gt;months&lt;/strong&gt; old) who were &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;already&lt;/span&gt; at a high risk of developing peanut allergy (as results of their parents having a similar allergy), were randomly fed food that contained peanuts or without it. Now this was interesting because parents tend to avoid feeding kids peanuts out of &lt;strong&gt;fear &lt;/strong&gt;that they may develop an allergy (interestingly, this is similar to parents not exposing their kids to dust, street food, god knows what else).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result – exactly what the proverbs tell us: Those who consumed the foods that had peanuts in them were far less likely to be allergic to peanuts when they turned 5. In fact this is fairly similar to why Israeli kids are less likely to be peanut allergic – the most popular snack in Israel is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bamba_(snack)&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bamba_(snack)', 'Bamba']);&quot;&gt;Bamba&lt;/a&gt;, which are essentially cheetos with the cheese replaced by peanut butter (as a way of ensuring kosher compliant food). Increases in levels of peanut-specific IgG4 antibody occurred predominantly in the peanut consumption group – remember, a lower ratio of peanut-specific IgG4:IgE were associated with peanut allergy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whose fault is this: well, the American Academy of Pediatrics in 2000 recommended that no maternal dietary restrictions during pregnancy were necessary &lt;strong&gt;with the exception of peanuts and tree nuts.&lt;/strong&gt; In 2008, the AAP published an updated guideline that simply &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2659557/&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2659557/', 'said']);&quot;&gt;said&lt;/a&gt; that “&lt;em&gt;found that in peanut allergic children there was no evidence of prenatal sensitization from the maternal diet…… delaying the introduction of foods that are considered to be highly allergic, such as fish, eggs, and foods containing peanut protein.&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, very interestingly, last month the AAP retracted its earlier guidelines and published &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aap.org/en-us/about-the-aap/aap-press-room/pages/AAP-Joins-in-Interim-Guidance-on-Introduction-of-Peanuts-for-High-Risk-Infants.aspx&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'https://www.aap.org/en-us/about-the-aap/aap-press-room/pages/AAP-Joins-in-Interim-Guidance-on-Introduction-of-Peanuts-for-High-Risk-Infants.aspx', 'new ones']);&quot;&gt;new ones&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The interim guidance summarizes the evidence that finds early peanut introduction is safe and effective in infants at high risk of peanut allergy. Health care providers should recommend introducing peanut-containing products into the diets of high-risk infants between ages 4 and 11 months. Because there is a risk that such infants could already be peanut-allergic, the guidance suggests that infants with early onset allergic disease, such as severe eczema or egg allergy, may benefit from an evaluation by an allergist, which could include allergy testing, and possibly an observed peanut ingestion. – See more at: https://www.aap.org/en-us/about-the-aap/aap-press-room/pages/AAP-Joins-in-Interim-Guidance-on-Introduction-of-Peanuts-for-High-Risk-Infants.aspx#sthash.AnJj77Se.dpuf&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what’s the current best practice ? feed more peanut chikki or peanut butter to your kid and avoid nut allergies in general.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html">There was a study designed by a team from King’s College London called Learning Early About Peanut Allergy (LEAP) .  It was interesting enought that there is a whole website now dedicated to this.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2015/10/77.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kids with short sleeping time have twice the risk of being overweight / obese latest meta-analysis says.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/kids-with-short-sleeping-time-have-twice-the-risk-of-being-overweight-obese-latest-meta-analysis-says-836/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kids with short sleeping time have twice the risk of being overweight / obese latest meta-analysis says." /><published>2015-09-19T19:55:15+05:30</published><updated>2015-09-19T19:55:15+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/kids-with-short-sleeping-time-have-twice-the-risk-of-being-overweight-obese-latest-meta-analysis-says</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/kids-with-short-sleeping-time-have-twice-the-risk-of-being-overweight-obese-latest-meta-analysis-says-836/">&lt;p&gt;Is Sleep Duration Associated With Childhood Obesity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25589359&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25589359', 'study']);&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;, which performs meta-analysis of 11 longitudinal studies, comprising 24,821 participants, revealed that subjects sleeping for short duration had twice the risk of being overweight/obese, compared with subjects sleeping for long duration (odds ratio 2.15; 95% confidence interval: 1.64–2.81).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;” This study prov&lt;span class=&quot;text_exposed_show&quot;&gt;ides evidence that short sleep duration in young subjects is significantly associated with future overweight/obesity,” scientists say. A related article is &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.researchgate.net/publication/5611575_Is_Sleep_Duration_Associated_With_Childhood_Obesity_A_Systematic_Review_and_Meta-analysis&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.researchgate.net/publication/5611575_Is_Sleep_Duration_Associated_With_Childhood_Obesity_A_Systematic_Review_and_Meta-analysis', 'here']);&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this topic needs to be looked at some depth, since this particular study is just a meta study… but I’m fairly likely to believe the conclusions. More sleep is much better than less sleep!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html">Is Sleep Duration Associated With Childhood Obesity?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Funny-Babies-Sleeping.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Credit Suisse thought leadership posts a study in favor of saturated fats</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/credit-suisse-thought-leadership-posts-a-study-in-favor-of-saturated-fats-845/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Credit Suisse thought leadership posts a study in favor of saturated fats" /><published>2015-09-19T18:01:33+05:30</published><updated>2015-09-19T18:01:33+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/credit-suisse-thought-leadership-posts-a-study-in-favor-of-saturated-fats</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/credit-suisse-thought-leadership-posts-a-study-in-favor-of-saturated-fats-845/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.credit-suisse.com/researchplus/ravDocView?docid=4CbnSI&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'https://plus.credit-suisse.com/researchplus/ravDocView?docid=4CbnSI', 'This']);&quot;&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is a document authored by Credit Suisse’s thought leadership series around health and nutrition. The document analyzes fat (both saturated and non-saturated ) intake over the past years, ingests over 400 research papers as well as detailed discussions with top experts around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important conclusion ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The big concern regarding eating cholesterol-rich foods (e.g. eggs) is completely without foundation.&lt;strong&gt;There is basically no link between the cholesterol we eat and the level of cholesterol in our blood.&lt;/strong&gt; This was already known thirty years ago and has been confirmed time and time again. Eating cholesterol rich foods has no negative effect on health in general or on risk of cardiovascular diseases (CVDs), in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Doctors and patients’ focus on “bad” and “good” cholesterol is superficial at best and most likely misleading. The most mentioned factors that doctors use to assess the risk of CVDs—total blood cholesterol (TC) and LDL cholesterol (the “bad” cholesterol)—are poor indicators of CVD risk. In women in particular, TC has zero predictive value if we look at all causes of death. Low blood cholesterol in men could be as bad as very high cholesterol. The best indicators are the size of LDL particles (pattern A or B) and the ratio of TG (triglycerides) to HDL (the “good” cholesterol). A VAP test to check your pattern A/B costs less than $100 in the U.S., yet few know of its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Based on medical and our own research we can conclude that the intake of saturated fat (butter, palm and coconut oil and lard) poses no risk to our health and particularly to the heart&lt;/strong&gt;. In the words of probably the most important epidemiological study published on the subject by SiriTarino et al: “There is no significant evidence for concluding that dietary saturated fat is associated with an increased risk of CHD or CVD.” Saturated fat is actually a healthy source of energy and it has a positive effect on the pattern A/B.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The main factor behind a high level of saturated fats in our blood is actually carbohydrates, not the amount of saturated fat we eat.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is not huge for me, since Fitosaurus has commented on this &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fitosaur.us/the-truth-about-saturated-fat-583/&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.fitosaur.us/the-truth-about-saturated-fat-583/', 'before']);&quot;&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;… &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fitosaur.us/cholesterol-good-officially-us-govt-guidelines-830/&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.fitosaur.us/cholesterol-good-officially-us-govt-guidelines-830/', 'multiple times']);&quot;&gt;multiple times&lt;/a&gt;. But this should act to further correct the bad dietary advice being doled out by the bagful these days. Especially in India, where an extremely high proportion of our diet consists of carbohydrates, we tend to demonize the wrong thing. We have way too much of low fat idlis and low fat dhoklas and fat free gulab jamuns. It is time to recognize and correct our diets.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html">This is a document authored by Credit Suisse’s thought leadership series around health and nutrition. The document analyzes fat (both saturated and non-saturated ) intake over the past years, ingests over 400 research papers as well as detailed discussions with top experts around the world.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/Butter.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The best exercise for triceps – the JM Press</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/the-best-exercise-for-triceps-the-jm-press-839/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The best exercise for triceps &amp;#8211; the JM Press" /><published>2015-03-01T08:15:10+05:30</published><updated>2015-03-01T08:15:10+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/the-best-exercise-for-triceps-the-jm-press</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/the-best-exercise-for-triceps-the-jm-press-839/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/barbell-jm-press-1024x576.jpg&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/barbell-jm-press-1024x576.jpg', '']);&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-841&quot; src=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/barbell-jm-press-1024x576-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;barbell-jm-press-1024x576&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Named for John Mark Blakeley – one of the trainers at the famous Westside Barbell. He holds 6 world records, is a 4 time world bench press champion and was also the 11th man in history to bench 700lb (raw).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A JM Press is a hybrid exercise for the triceps, often performed on a flat bench with a barbell. Its blend between a close grip bench press and a triceps extension. Its designed to make your triceps extremely strong for bench pressing and really helps to strengthen the tendons and get the joints and build them up to handle heavy loads. Whilst the movement hits all three triceps heads (triceps brachii) there is a particular focus and feeling on the long head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise avoids any engagement with elbows and shoulders which allows any damage to your tendons.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/barbell-jm-press-1024x576-624x351.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cholesterol is good again… (Officially. US Govt Guidelines)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/cholesterol-good-officially-us-govt-guidelines-830/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cholesterol is good again&amp;#8230; (Officially. US Govt Guidelines)" /><published>2015-02-11T18:18:50+05:30</published><updated>2015-02-11T18:18:50+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/cholesterol-good-officially-us-govt-guidelines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/cholesterol-good-officially-us-govt-guidelines-830/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/imrs.jpg&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/imrs.jpg', '']);&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-831&quot; src=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/imrs-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;imrs&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is huge – the US government’s Food and Drug Administration has &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2015/02/10/feds-poised-to-withdraw-longstanding-warnings-about-dietary-cholesterol/&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.washingtonpost.com/blogs/wonkblog/wp/2015/02/10/feds-poised-to-withdraw-longstanding-warnings-about-dietary-cholesterol/', ' officially decided to withdraw warning AGAINST dietary cholesterol']);&quot;&gt;officially decided to withdraw warning AGAINST dietary cholesterol&lt;/a&gt;. Now, you can go ahead and eat all the egg yolks you want without worrying. This was always scientifically incorrect, but now there is widespread consensus around it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Fitosaur.us, we have tried to maintain a &lt;a href=&quot;fitosaur.us/the-truth-about-saturated-fat-583/&quot;&gt;balanced viewpoint&lt;/a&gt; around cholesterol and saturated fat for a long time. We sure are glad to see it validated!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The nation’s top nutrition advisory panel has decided to drop its caution about eating cholesterol-laden food, a move that could undo almost 40 years of government warnings about its consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The group’s finding that cholesterol in the diet need no longer be considered a “nutrient of concern” stands in contrast to the committee’s findings five years ago, the last time it convened. During those proceedings, as in previous years, the panel deemed the issue of excess cholesterol in the American diet a public health concern.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The finding follows an evolution of thinking among many nutritionists who now believe that, for healthy adults, eating foods high in cholesterol may not significantly affect the level of cholesterol in the blood or increase the risk of heart disease.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/imrs-624x416.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Diet fiction – multiple small meals a day and exercise to lose weight</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/multiple-meals-a-day-exercise-809/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Diet fiction &amp;#8211; multiple small meals a day and exercise to lose weight" /><published>2014-08-03T08:25:12+05:30</published><updated>2014-08-03T08:25:12+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/multiple-meals-a-day-exercise</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/multiple-meals-a-day-exercise-809/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/multipleburgers.jpg&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/multipleburgers.jpg', '']);&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-817&quot; src=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/multipleburgers-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;multiple small meals&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular advice given as a reply to the question “how do I lost weight quickly”, is to recommend multiple small meals a day. This theory is extremely popular especially because of the recommendation of several celebrity dieticians who swear by this method. Let us look at the real science behind this theory&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;aspect-of-satietysatisfaction&quot;&gt;Aspect of satiety/satisfaction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First the fundamental issue with the “6 meals a day” diet of several celebrity dieticians – what most people miss out is that actually overall calories are dropped in these kinds of diets. The 6 meals a day does not increase amount of food, but actually tries to fool the body into being satiated with less…. by eating more frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is the official &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.jissn.com/content/8/1/4&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.jissn.com/content/8/1/4', '&amp;#8220;position statement&amp;#8221; of the International Society of Sports Nutrition']);&quot;&gt;“position statement” of the &lt;strong&gt;International Society of Sports Nutrition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  Position Statement: Admittedly, research to date examining the physiological effects of meal frequency in humans is somewhat limited. More specifically, data that has specifically examined the impact of meal frequency on body composition, training adaptations, and performance in physically active individuals and athletes is scant. Until more research is available in the physically active and athletic populations, definitive conclusions cannot be made. However, within the confines of the current scientific literature, we assert that:
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  1. Increasing meal frequency does not appear to favorably change body composition in sedentary populations.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  2. If protein levels are adequate, increasing meal frequency during periods of hypoenergetic dieting may preserve lean body mass in athletic populations.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  3. Increased meal frequency appears to have a positive effect on various blood markers of health, particularly LDL cholesterol, total cholesterol, and insulin.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  4. Increased meal frequency does not appear to significantly enhance diet induced thermogenesis, total energy expenditure or resting metabolic rate.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  5. Increasing meal frequency appears to help decrease hunger and improve appetite control.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  There are various studies around this aspect &amp;#8211; and several of them disagree on the satiety of high meal frequency vs low meal frequency. However, &lt;strong&gt;all&lt;/strong&gt; of them agree that meal frequency&lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt; does not&lt;/span&gt; help in metabolism or body composition.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;correlation-is-not-causation&quot;&gt;Correlation is not causation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of studies that show that because two things are related, they are caused by each other. For example,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22218154&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22218154', 'Less frequent eating predicts greater BMI and waist circumference in female adolescents.']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less frequent eating predicts greater BMI and waist circumference in female adolescents.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  A lower eating frequency predicts a greater gain in adiposity in adolescent females. &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;Intervention trials are needed to test if changing the frequency of eating can affect obesity risk.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the studies most often quoted to prove that frequency of eating has a reasonable correlation with obesity. Obviously, they are correlated, but could happen for a variety of different reasons – for example, the subjects need to be double checked for smoking (which reduces appetite) and several other factors that could have been indirectly causing obesity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-about-impact-of-meal-frequency-on-other-metabolic-markers-blood-lipid-level-cholesterol-level-etc&quot;&gt;What about impact of meal frequency on other metabolic markers (blood lipid level, cholesterol level, etc.)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0038632&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0038632', 'Effects of Meal Frequency on Metabolic Profiles and Substrate Partitioning in Lean Healthy Males']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects of Meal Frequency on Metabolic Profiles and Substrate Partitioning in Lean Healthy Males&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The higher rise and subsequently fall of insulin in the LowFrequency diet did not lead to a higher fat oxidation as hypothesized. The LowFrequency diet decreased glucose levels throughout the day (AUC) indicating glycemic improvements. RestingMetabolicRate and appetite control increased in the LowFrequency diet, which can be relevant for body weight control on the long term.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24838678&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24838678', 'Eating two larger meals a day (breakfast and lunch) is more effective than six smaller meals in a reduced-energy regimen for patients with type 2 diabetes: a randomised crossover study.']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eating two larger meals a day (breakfast and lunch) is more effective than six smaller meals in a reduced-energy regimen for patients with type 2 diabetes: a randomised crossover study.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  Eating only breakfast and lunch reduced body weight, HFC, fasting plasma glucose, C-peptide and glucagon, and increased OGIS, more than the same caloric restriction split into six meals. These results suggest that, for type 2 diabetic patients on a hypoenergetic diet, eating larger breakfasts and lunches may be more beneficial than six smaller meals during the day.
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24936481&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24936481', 'The Effects of 6 Isocaloric Meals on Body Weight, Lipid Profiles, Leptin, and Adiponectin in Overweight Subjects (BMI &amp;gt; 25).']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Effects of 6 Isocaloric Meals on Body Weight, Lipid Profiles, Leptin, and Adiponectin in Overweight Subjects (BMI &amp;gt; 25).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;The 6 isocaloric meal pattern led to a reduction in BMI, lipid profiles (total cholesterol, LDL-C, triglyceride), and leptin concentrations and an increase in HDL and adiponectin compared to the normal diet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the hell ? None of these studies seem to agree with each other – all of them have fairly conflicting results. So what do I believe in ?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is precisely the problem I wanted to illustrate – just increasing meal frequency and eating more will actually cause more trouble… while changing meal frequency while eating the same has no predictability, because it depends on so many other factors (your particular diet, age, diabetes condition, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what works ? &lt;strong&gt;Exercise and simultaneously reducing your calories.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;my-belief-8211-the-pancreatic-theory&quot;&gt;My belief – the pancreatic theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Warning: this is what I personally believe in. As I listed above, the published research has not come to a settling conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt;There are two phases for insulin secretion.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt;The first phase lasts for approximately 10 minutes: in this, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt; phase 1 this stored insulin is released.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt;In phase 2 the pancreas produces more insulin.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt; Eating every 2-3 hours puts a strain on the pancreas because it is unable to produce the stored insulin for phase 1. In fact, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22834840&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22834840', 'problems in Phase 1 is an independent predictor of type 2 diabetes ']);&quot;&gt;problems in Phase 1 is an independent predictor of type 2 diabetes &lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt;One of the reasons is this : As we eat, leptin levels should rise, increasing &lt;strong&gt;satiety&lt;/strong&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14749281&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/14749281', 'communicating with the pancreatic cells to stop producing insulin']);&quot;&gt;communicating with the pancreatic cells to stop producing insulin&lt;/a&gt;. On the other hand, an increase in insulin increases leptin. If we continually secrete insulin, increasing leptin, we could be at risk for leptin + insulin resistance and metabolic syndrome. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, &lt;span style=&quot;color: #3e3e3e;&quot;&gt;Glucagon communicates with the liver to release its stored glucose to maintain blood sugar levels. Insulin and glucagon cannot be present in the bloodstream at the same time, so this occurs roughly 3 hours after eating a meal. Glucagon triggers fat burning –  If we consume a meal every 2-3 hours glucagon is never released (because insulin is continually released) and we never enter this fat burning period. This is why I prefer a fasting based diet (alternate day fasting or intermittent fasting – a minimum 16 to 24 hour fast) to any other diet method.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exercise-is-not-enough&quot;&gt;Exercise is not enough&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;here’s what each kind of exercise burns, in terms of calories&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;heading4&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: bold; color: #000000;&quot;&gt; 400 to 500+ per hour&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  Elliptical Training: Burns 575&lt;br /&gt; Mountain Biking: Burns 545&lt;br /&gt; Circuit Training (hard, with some cardio between sets): Burns 510&lt;br /&gt; Cross-Country Skiing (moderate): Burns 510&lt;br /&gt; Rowing (moderate, stationary machine): Burns 450&lt;br /&gt; Swimming (freestyle laps, easy): Burns 450
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;heading4&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: bold; color: #000000;&quot;&gt; 300 to 400 per hour&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  Weight Lifting (dumbbells or machines): Burns 385&lt;br /&gt; Hiking (without a pack): Burns 385&lt;br /&gt; Walk-Jog Intervals: Burns 385&lt;br /&gt; Body-Sculpting Class: Burns 350&lt;br /&gt; Kayaking: Burns 320&lt;br /&gt; Jazz Dance: Burns 305&lt;br /&gt; Power Walking (very briskly, 4 mph): Burns 320
&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;heading4&quot; style=&quot;font-weight: bold; color: #000000;&quot;&gt; 150 to 300 per hour&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  Flamenco, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fitnessmagazine.com/videos/body-parts/stomach.htm&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.fitnessmagazine.com/videos/body-parts/stomach.htm', 'Belly']);&quot; style=&quot;color: #3e3181;&quot;&gt;Belly&lt;/a&gt;, or Swing Dancing: Burns 290&lt;br /&gt; Shooting Hoops: Burns 290&lt;br /&gt; Golfing (walking and carrying clubs): Burns 290&lt;br /&gt; Rebounding (jogging on a mini tramp): Burns 290&lt;br /&gt; Water Aerobics: Burns 255&lt;br /&gt; Tai Chi: Burns 255&lt;br /&gt; Brisk Walking: (3.5 mph) Burns 245&lt;br /&gt; Pilates (general mat workout): Burns 160&lt;br /&gt; Yoga (Hatha): Burns 160
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  So, what does 500 calories get us ? 1 bowl of &lt;em&gt;healthy &lt;/em&gt;poha (150 calories) + 2 slices of &lt;em&gt;healthy&lt;/em&gt; multigrain bread (160) and small cup of cornflakes with milk (160 calories).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  To reiterate &amp;#8211; one hour of hard circuit training is going to be completely negated by a paltry breakfast. Oh and let&amp;#8217;s be serious here &amp;#8211; most of us get to 200 calories per hour (with brisk walks, jogs and yoga)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  The hard fact is that exercise is superb for cardiovascular health, to build muscle, to build lung aerobic capacity and to even fight cancer (yes!). But it is not good enough to lose weight because it is &lt;span style=&quot;text-decoration: underline;&quot;&gt;virtually impossible to exercise more than what you can eat.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  The EPOC argument &amp;#8211; &lt;span style=&quot;color: #545454;&quot;&gt;Excess post-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-weight: bold; color: #545454;&quot;&gt;exercise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #545454;&quot;&gt; oxygen consumption or continuing-to-burn-fat-after-exercise &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17101527&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17101527', 'Effects of exercise intensity and duration on the excess post-exercise oxygen consumption.']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects of exercise intensity and duration on the excess post-exercise oxygen consumption.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  However, even those studies incorporating exercise stimuli resulting in prolonged EPOC durations have identified that the EPOC comprises only 6-15% of the net total oxygen cost of the exercise.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  So 15% of 500 calories (in a one hour circuit training) is 75 calories = 1 slice of bread.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  Conclusion &amp;#8211; to lose weight, drop your calories : use any method you want &amp;#8211; intermittent fasting, alternate day fasting (my current favorite) or 6 meals a day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;
  Exercise for overall health, power and strength.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/multipleburgers-624x351.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Total darkness at night key to success of breast cancer therapy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/total-darkness-night-key-success-breast-cancer-therapy-807/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Total darkness at night key to success of breast cancer therapy" /><published>2014-07-29T21:02:55+05:30</published><updated>2014-07-29T21:02:55+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/total-darkness-night-key-success-breast-cancer-therapy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/total-darkness-night-key-success-breast-cancer-therapy-807/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/dark-sky.jpg&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/dark-sky.jpg', '']);&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-821&quot; src=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/dark-sky-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;dark-sky&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25062775&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25062775', 'Circadian and Melatonin Disruption by Exposure to Light at Night Drives Intrinsic Resistance to Tamoxifen Therapy in Breast Cancer.']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Circadian and Melatonin Disruption by Exposure to Light at Night Drives Intrinsic Resistance to Tamoxifen Therapy in Breast Cancer.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Exposure to light at night, which shuts off nighttime production of the hormone melatonin, renders breast cancer completely resistant to tamoxifen, a widely used breast cancer drug, says a new study. Melatonin by itself delayed the formation of tumors and significantly slowed their growth, researchers report, but tamoxifen caused a dramatic regression of tumors in animals with either high nighttime levels of melatonin during complete darkness or those receiving melatonin supplementation during dim light at night exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;comment&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color: #000000;&quot;&gt;tamoxifen caused a dramatic regression of tumors in animals with either high nighttime levels of melatonin during complete darkness or those receiving melatonin supplementation during dim light at night exposure.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is huge – this means that sleeping with lights off at night is much more important than previously thought. Women may be much more susceptible to cancer with lights on than with lights off.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html"></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/dark-sky.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Protein vs Resistance training – what actually results in muscle growth</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/protein-vs-resistance-training-actually-results-muscle-growth-799/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Protein vs Resistance training &amp;#8211; what actually results in muscle growth" /><published>2014-07-24T16:23:57+05:30</published><updated>2014-07-24T16:23:57+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/protein-vs-resistance-training-actually-results-muscle-growth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/protein-vs-resistance-training-actually-results-muscle-growth-799/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/featured.jpg&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/featured.jpg', '']);&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft size-thumbnail wp-image-802&quot; src=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/featured-300x300.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;protein powder&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;There has been an interesting group of studies that casts doubts over the contribution of protein towards muscle growth versus hard, solid resistance training. At the end of the day, whether you believe it or not (and even with error margins), I think what it say is that – it doesnt matter shit that you miss eating your protein on a few days. It also doesnt matter to sit inside a gym and keep sipping your expensive protein shake while working out (also known as peri-workout nutrition, debunked &lt;a href=&quot;http://fitosaur.us/when-should-you-drink-your-protein-shake-444/&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://fitosaur.us/when-should-you-drink-your-protein-shake-444/', 'here']);&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). But it matters a lot that you put in a lot of solid resistance training, even when you are sleepy or tired.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24919692&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24919692', 'Dirks, Marlou L., et al. &amp;#8220;Skeletal muscle disuse atrophy is not attenuated by dietary protein supplementation in healthy older men.&amp;#8221;']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;fbPhotoPageCaption&quot; class=&quot;fbPhotosPhotoCaption&quot; tabindex=&quot;0&quot; data-ft=&quot;{&amp;quot;type&amp;quot;:45,&amp;quot;tn&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;*G&amp;quot;}&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;hasCaption&quot;&gt;Dirks, Marlou L., et al. “Skeletal muscle disuse atrophy is not attenuated by dietary protein supplementation in healthy older men.”&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;We hypothesized that protein supplementation twice daily would preserve muscle mass during a short period of limb immobilization.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In the present study, we found that only 5 d of muscle disuse lead to substantial loss of muscle mass  in older individuals. These data are in line with recent data from our group in which we observed similar muscle mass and strength losses in younger individuals&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;In the present study, we found that only 5 d of muscle disuse lead to substantial loss of muscle mass  in older individuals. These data are in line with recent data from our group in which we observed similar muscle mass and strength losses in younger individuals&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Increasing dietary protein intake from 1.1 to 1.6 g did not attenuate the loss of muscle mass or strength observed during a 5-d period of leg immobilization. The apparent discrepancy between the outcome of the present study and previous work in prolonged bed rest studies&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;may be attributed to differences in protein intake in the control group. In the present study, the control group retained normal habitual energy and protein intake  whereas the PRO group was administered additional supplementation efits of amino acid supplementation on muscle mass main-tenance, the control groups generally consumed dietary protein at a concentration no higher than 0.8 g&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Consequently, we speculate that maintaining dietary protein intake is required to prevent muscle loss during disuse, but that increasing dietary protein intake above habitual concentrations does not further alleviate muscle loss during disuse.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23442287&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent', 'outbound-article', 'http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23442287', 'Walter AA, Herda TJ, Costa PB, Ryan ED, Stout JR, Cramer JT. Muscle Performance, Size, And Safety Responses After Eight Weeks Of Resistance Training And Protein Supplementation: A Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial.']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Walter AA, Herda TJ, Costa PB, Ryan ED, Stout JR, Cramer JT. Muscle Performance, Size, And Safety Responses After Eight Weeks Of Resistance Training And Protein Supplementation: A Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled Clinical Trial.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;One hundred and six men were randomized into 5 groups: low-volume resistance training with bioenhanced whey protein (BWPLV; n = 22), moderate-volume resistance training with BWP (BWPMV; n = 20), moderate-volume resistance training with standard whey protein (SWPMV; n = 22), &lt;strong&gt;moderate-volume resistance training with a placebo&lt;/strong&gt; (PLA; n = 21), or &lt;strong&gt;moderate-volume resistance training with no supplementation&lt;/strong&gt; (CON; n = 21).&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This study indicated that 8 weeks of resistance training improved muscle performance and size similarly among groups regardless of supplementation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the study that caused a lot of controversy – about how a properly administered trial actually failed to prove any correlation of muscle supplementation (even the mind-game placebo variety) with muscle growth ! This is incredibly fascinating and needs to be studied more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amherst.edu/system/files/media/Effects_of_Different_Dietary_Proteins_and_Amino.5.pdf&quot; onclick=&quot;_gaq.push(['_trackEvent','download','https://www.amherst.edu/system/files/media/Effects_of_Different_Dietary_Proteins_and_Amino.5.pdf']);&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt; Effects of Different Dietary Proteins and Amino Acids on Skeletal Muscle Hypertrophy in Young Adults After Resistance Exercise: A Systematic Review&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;span data-ft=&quot;{&amp;quot;tn&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;K&amp;quot;}&quot; data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;UFICommentBody&quot; data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0&quot;&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.0&quot;&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.0.$end:0:$0:0&quot;&gt; “It is possible that the beginners in the study by Herda et al. could have benefited from their initial sensitivity to RE, resultin&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.3&quot;&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.3.0&quot;&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.3.0.$end:0:$0:0&quot;&gt;g in significant hypertrophy despite sub-optimal nutritional circumstances”. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span data-ft=&quot;{&amp;quot;tn&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;K&amp;quot;}&quot; data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;UFICommentBody&quot; data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0&quot;&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.3&quot;&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.3.0&quot;&gt;&lt;span data-reactid=&quot;.3i.1:3:1:$comment801217823243703_801280659904086:0.0.$right.0.$left.0.0.1:$comment-body.0.3.0.$end:0:$0:0&quot;&gt;But this is an interesting study no doubt – that hard training &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; outclass expensive supplements (in third world countries). Having said that, please do note that a protein-centric diet has many advantages for diabetes control and weight loss (however calorie restriction is again the best way to achieve those)&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>admin</name></author><summary type="html">There has been an interesting group of studies that casts doubts over the contribution of protein towards muscle growth versus hard, solid resistance training. At the end of the day, whether you believe it or not (and even with error margins), I think what it say is that – it doesnt matter shit that you miss eating your protein on a few days. It also doesnt matter to sit inside a gym and keep sipping your expensive protein shake while working out (also known as peri-workout nutrition, debunked here). But it matters a lot that you put in a lot of solid resistance training, even when you are sleepy or tired.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/featured.jpg" /></entry></feed>
